[
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Write on Sūratun- NaṢr (Q.110) either in Arabic or transliteration, translate it into English and comment on it.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Transliteration</p><p>Bismillāhir Raḥmānir Raḥīm</p><p>*Idhā jā'a naṣrullāhi wal-fatḥu</p><p>*Wa ra'aytan-Nāsa yadkhulūna fī dīnillāh afwājā.</p><p>* Fasabbiḥi biḥamdi Rabbika wastaghfirhu innahu kāna tawwābā.</p><p>Translation</p><p>In the name of Allah, the most Gracious, the most Merciful.</p><p>*When Allah's help and victory come</p><p>*And you see men embracing His religion in multitudes.</p><p>*So glorify the praises of your Lord and seek His forgiveness, certainly, He is ever ready to forgive.</p><p>Comment</p><p>*Sūratun Naṣr is aMadinan Chapter.</p><p>*It contains three verses</p><p>*It takes its name from the first verse of the chapter.</p><p>*It is the last chapter to be revealed in its completeness.</p><p>*It reminds one of the fulfillments of Allah's promise of help and victory for Islam</p><p>*Victory comes with perseverance.</p><p>*Allah helps those who fight in His cause.</p><p>*We should confess our frailties and seek Allah's forgiveness.</p><p>*Glorification of Allah should be at all times.</p><p>*Allah accepts sincere repentance from His servants.</p><p>*It reminds one that Allah's promises will never fail</p><p>*It reminds one that Allah is ever-ready to forgive us our sins if we seek forgiveness from Him.</p><p>*We should learn the habit of forgiving those who offend us.</p><p>*Assistance should be sought from Allah alone.</p><p>*Mankind should attribute success to Allah</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Describe the circumstances that made cUthmān b. cĀffān earn the title Dhu-Nurayn.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>cUthmān b. cAffān was the the third successor of the Prophet (S.A.W.) born in the year 573 C.E.( Introduction)</p><p>*The title Dhū-Nūrayn means the possessor of two lights.</p><p>*This title was given based on his close relationship with the Prophet (S.A.W.)</p><p>*The closeness was such that the Prophet (S.A.W.) gave him his daughter Ruqayyah in marriage.</p><p>*He and his wife Ruqayyah were among the first batch of Muslims to migrate to Abyssinia.</p><p>*On their return to Makkah, Ruqayyah died.</p><p>*cUthmān decided not to re-marry after the death of Ruqayyah.</p><p>*This is because he could not take anyone else as a father- in-law after the Prophet (S.A.W.)</p><p>*The Prophet (S.A.W.) loved him so much that he gave him another daughter Ummu Kulthūm in marriage.</p><p>*This was in the third year of Hijrah.</p><p>*Ummu Kulthūm too died in the fourth year of Hijrah.</p><p>*The holy Prophet (S.A.W.) expressed his admiration for his conduct after the death of  his second wife.</p><p>*As a result he remarked that, if he had another unmarried daughter, he would have married her to him.</p><p>*His marriage with two daughters of the Prophet (S.A.W.) earned him the honorific title Dhū-Nūrayn.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>State the conditions that necessitate Ghusl in Islam and describe how it is performed.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Ghusl is an Arabic term referring to the full-body ritual purification mandatory before the performance of various rituals and prayers. (Introduction)</p><p>Ghusl</p><p>*Janābah.</p><p>*Ḥayḍa</p><p>*Nifās.</p><p>*Janāzah</p><p>*Dukhūlul-Islam.</p><p>*Jumcah ( Friday prayer).</p><p>*After washing a corpse.</p><p>*Before entering the state of Ihrām.</p><p>*cĪdayn ( Adhā and Fitr).</p><p>How to perform Ghusl</p><p>*Get clean water.</p><p>*Begin with the intention of performing Ghusl for purification.</p><p>*Saying the Basmalah silently.</p><p>*Wash the hands up to the wrists.</p><p>*Wash your private parts.</p><p>*Wash your hands to clean off the dirt.</p><p>*Perform ablution</p><p>*Wash your head down to the roots of the hair.</p><p>*Divide your body into two parts.</p><p>*Wash the right side then the left.</p><p>*Pour water over your entire body.</p><p>*Move away from the area you just performed the &lt;em&gt;Ghusl&lt;/em&gt; and wash your feet.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>(a)Define the term Shirk</p><p>(b)Explain with three examples each, the two types of Shirk.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>(a)Shirk means associating partner(s) with Allah and it is the opposite of   Monotheism (Tawḥīd).</p><p>(b) Types:</p><p>*Shirkul- Akbar(Major Shirk).</p><p>*Shirkul- Aṣghar (Minor Shirk).</p><p>Shirkul- Akbar is a major Shirk which constitute apostasy.</p><p>Shirk condemns the persons who practice it to Hell.</p><p>Examples:</p><p>*Atheism- Disbelief in Allah.</p><p>*Idol Worship.</p><p>*Hero Worship.</p><p>*Dualism.</p><p>*Trinity.</p><p>*Ancestral worship.</p><p>*Making a vow with other being other than Allah.</p><p>*Seeking supernatural help and aid from other than Allah.</p><p>*Making a middle- man (intercessor) between oneself and Allah.</p><p>*Palm reading or fortune telling.</p><p>Shirkul-Aṣghar  is a minor shirk which does not constitute apostasy.</p><p>Its defects could lead to major Shirk.</p><p>Examples:</p><p>*Utterances, such as swearing by another deity other than Allah.</p><p>*Actions, such as wearing a ring or an amulet to ward off evil.</p><p>*&gt;Ar-Riyā'u- show off.</p><p>*Hidden Shirk i.e. inwardly dissatisfied with the decree of Allah.</p><p>*Belief in superstitions.</p><p> </p><p> \n</p><p> \n</p><p> \n</p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Discuss the role of Huffaz in the preservation of the Qur'ān.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Ḥuffāẓ (Ḥāfiẓ) literally means \"guardian\" or \"memorizer\". It is a term used by Muslims for someone who has completely memorized the Qur'ān.Ḥuffāz were the memorizers of the Qur'ān.</p><p>*The Prophet (S.A.W.) was the first Ḥāfiẓ.</p><p>*He dictated the verses of the Qur'ān to others who later memorized it.</p><p>*The Ḥuffāẓ wrote the revelation down on different objects such as tree barks, stones, animal skins, bones e.t.c</p><p>*Majority of the companions memorized the Qur'ān.</p><p>*The four principal memorizers under the Prophet's guidance were: Abdullāh b. Mas'ūd, Salim Mawla Abī Hudhayfah, Mu'adh b. Jabal and Ubayy b. Ka'ab.</p><p>*The Prophet (S.A.W.) sent seventy of such memorizers as instructors of the Qur'ān to certain tribes.</p><p>*Victory at the Battle of Yamāmah is attributed to the Ḥuffāẓ although a great number of them lost their lives.</p><p>*The Ḥuffāẓ's contribution during the compilation of the Qur'ān was quite significant.</p><p>*The leader of the committee for the compilation, Zayd b. Thabit was a Ḥāfiẓ.</p><p>*Upon the collection of the various fragments of the Qur'ān, their place and authenticity were determined by the Ḥuffāẓ.</p><p>*The Ḥuffāẓ recited portions from the Qur'ān in Ṣalāt and other devotional practices at social gathering.</p><p>*The Ḥufāz guided other Muslims on Qur'ānic memorization.</p><p>*The Ḥuffāẓ also played a leading role to standardize the variations in reading the Qur'ān.</p><p>*The role played by the Ḥuffāẓ stands the test of time.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Innal- Halala bayyinun wa innal- Harama bayyinun, wabaynahuma umurun mushtabihat  la ya lamuhunna kathirun mina- Nas.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>*That which is lawful is plain and that which is unlawful is plain and between the two are doubtful matters about which not many people know.</p><p>*It is obligatory upon Muslims to engage in lawful actions.</p><p>*Lawful and unlawful things are clear.</p><p>*There are also doubtful things in regards to permissible acts.</p><p>*Other permissible acts are also unclear.</p><p>*It is better to avoid doubtful acts.</p><p>*Engaging in doubtful acts may incur Allah's displeasure</p><p>*For he who deals with the doubtful acts may one day actually deal with the unlawful ones.</p><p>*Such actions may lead to regrettable ends.</p><p>*Lawful acts are highly meritorious and rewarding.</p><p>*Unlawful acts are highly detested by Allah and punishable before Him.</p><p>*Avoidance of ambiguity protects one's religion and integrity.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Comment on the first four verses of Sūratul Fātiḥah (Q.1:1-4).</p>",
        "answer": "<p>*Sūratul Fātiḥah is the first chapter of the Holy Qur&amp;rsquo;an and it contains seven oft-  repeated verses.</p><p>*Thanks be to Allah Lord of the worlds.</p><p>*The Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.</p><p>*Master of the Day of Judgement.</p><p>*All human acts are expected to start with the name of Allah.</p><p>*Gratitude must be expressed to Allah for His bounties.</p><p>*Allah created and owns the universe with its creatures, (living and non-living)</p><p>*The Day of Judgement is real.</p><p>*Allah will preside over the judgement on the Last Day.</p><p>*The Day of Judgement confirms resurrection.</p><p>*All human beings will account for their deeds on that day</p><p>*The wrong-doers will lament and go to Hell.</p><p>*Allah&amp;rsquo;s judgement is fair and unquestionable.</p><p>*All humankind are at his Mercy.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Examine the significance of the year of year of Elephant (570 C.E.)</p>",
        "answer": "<p>*The event of the Elephant refers to an attempt to pull down the Kacbah in 570 C.E.</p><p>*It occurred when Abdul-Muṭṭalib was the head of Quraysh</p><p>*Abraha al-Ashram was then the Abyssinia viceroy of Yemen.</p><p> </p><p>*This is because of the political and economic significance of the pilgrimage as well as the religious leadership of Makkah.</p><p>*So he built an elaborate cathedral in Sanāc the capital of Yemen.</p><p>*The motive was to attract pilgrims to it instead of the kacbah.</p><p>*An Arab was said to have profaned this cathederal.</p><p>*He decided to march on Makkah to pull down the Kacbah in retaliation.</p><p>*Elephants and other war implements were obtained to execute the plan.</p><p>*Allah, the Owner of the House protected it.</p><p>*He sent flocks of birds with baked stones to destroy the attackers.</p><p>*The rest fled back to Abyssinia disappointed.</p><p>*Sūratul Fīl (Q.107) refers to the event.</p><p>*Prophet Muhammad (S.A.W.) was born in that year.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Outline the conditions for the authenticating  of  Hadith.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The Muḥāddithūn have stipulated certain conditions for the authentication of hadith.</p><p>*The Hadith must be accompanied by an Isnād (chain of narrators) with the authority under whom it was transmitted.</p><p>*The Hadith must be traceable to the Prophet (S.A.W.).</p><p>*The Isnād must be continous and uninterrupted.</p><p>*Every link in the Isnād must be known to be upright persons (cādilūn).</p><p>* of the persons in the Isnād must be implicated in forgery, sectarian, political and theological disputes.</p><p>*The narrators of the hadith must be a contemporary of the teacher on whose authority the hadith is related.</p><p>*The narrators of the Hadith must possess a retentive memory.</p><p>*The narrator must not be totally unknown (Majhūl).</p><p>*The Matn (text of hadith) must not contradict the Qurān.</p><p>*The Matn must be in agreement with reason.</p><p>*The hadith must be historical and it should not fail the test of historical evidence.</p><p>*The Matn of hadith must not extol the virtues of a particular tribe.</p><p>*The Matn must not predict the future events or dates.</p><p>*Both the Matn and Isnād of the hadith must be clear of subtle and hidden defects.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Discuss the teachings of Islam on Shirk.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>*Shirk (polytheism) is associating partner (s) with Allah.</p><p>*There are two forms of Shirk in Islam.</p><p>*Shirkul-Akbar (the major Shirk).</p><p>*Shirkul-Aṣghar (the minor Shirk).</p><p>*Committing Shirkul-Akbar takes one outside the fold of Islam (Kufr).</p><p>*Committing Shrkul-Aṣghar makes one a disobedient Muslim but does not take him out of Islam.</p><p>*Shirk is a grievous sin (Q.4:48).</p><p>*Example of Shirk al-Akbar is the denial of the existence of Allah.</p><p>*Other forms of Shirk include: Humanism, Trinity, Ancestor/Hero worship, Natural phenomena etc.</p><p>*The issue of Trinity is decisive on idol-worship (Q.107).</p><p>*Examples of Shirkul- aṣghar is Riyā; (show-off, eye service etc).</p><p>*One should disobey parents if they invite him to practice Shirk.</p><p>*Shirk is regarded as the highest form of hypocrisy (Q.3:13).</p><p>*The opposite of Shirk is Tawḥīd (Monotheism).</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>(a)Comment on the following verses:</p><p>*Iyyāka nacbudu wa iyyāka  nastacīn. (Q.1:5)</p><p>*Alaysa Llāhu bi aḥkamil hākimīn. (Q.95:8)</p><p>*Innā anzalnāhu fī laylatil Qadr. (Q.97:1)</p><p> </p>",
        "answer": "<p>*It is the fifth verse of Sūratul Fātiḥah.</p><p>*It means: &amp;ldquo;Thee alone do we worship and from Thee alone we seek for help:</p><p>*Man should worship none but Allah.</p><p>*In worship, man is not to associate partner(s) with Allah.</p><p>*Associating partner(s) with Allah is a major and unpardonable sin.</p><p>*Humankind&amp;rsquo;s source of help is Allah.</p><p>*Those who seek help from sources other than Allah are on the wrong path</p><p>*Such persons incur Allah&amp;rsquo;s displeasure. </p><p> </p><p>- It is the last verses of Sūratut –Tīn.</p><p>- It means: Is Allah not the best of Judges?</p><p>- Allah;s judgement is straight and fair.</p><p>- Human judgement is full of flaws.</p><p>- Those who flout Allah;s regulations are to be punished.</p><p>- The law-abiding ones will enjoy unending reward.</p><p>- In Allah;s court, there are no lawyers to argue a case.</p><p>- One cannot also deny wrong- doing if one indeed committed it.</p><p>- It is the opening verse of Sūratul- Qadr</p><p>- It means: we have revealed it on the Night of Power.</p><p>-The objectof revelation is the Qur;ān.</p><p>-It was on the Lawḥul-Maḥfūz (Heavenly preserved Tablet).</p><p>- It was kept in the &lt;em&gt;Baytul- cIzza</p><p>- The revelation began in the year 610 C.E. at Cave Hira.</p><p>- The revelation to the Prophet was through the agency of Jibrīl.</p><p>- The revelation ended in 632 C.E.</p><p>- The compilation of the Qur;ān started in the reign of Caliph Abū-Bakar.</p><p>- It was standardization during the rule of cUthmān b. cAffān.</p><p> </p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "irk",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Describe the performance of Tawāf during Hajj.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>*Tawāf involves going round the Kacbah seven times in a state of purity.</p><p>*It is the performed for Ḥajj and cUmrah.</p><p>*There are essentially three types but perfomed in the same manner.</p><p>*These are:Tawāf –Qudūm (Arrival Tawāf)</p><p>*Its time of performance depends on when the pilgrim arrives at Makkah.</p><p>*It is to be performed before the standing at cArafah.</p><p>*The second Tawāf is variously called Tawāf al-Ifadah, or Tawāf az-Ziyārah or Tawāf ar-Rukn.</p><p>*It is compulsory of the three kinds.</p><p>*It is performed on the Day of cId al-Aḍhā.</p><p>*The final Tawāf is Tawāf al-Wada (farewell Tawāf).</p><p>*It is performed when a pilgrim first perfoms ritual bath.</p><p>*The pilgrim begins and ends the movement from the Ḥajar al-Aswad.</p><p>*The pilgrim begins by saying: Bismillahi Allāhu Akbar.</p><p>*The Black stone is kissed, touched or signalled at every round of the circumambulation.</p><p>    </p><p>*The pilgrim touches the Rukni Yamāni in every circuit.</p><p>*The pilgrim also recites certain supplications during the Tawāf.</p><p>*Pilgrims do the first three rounds faster than the last four of the seven rounds.</p><p>*Two Rakcah of Nāfilah is to be observed at Maqām Ibrāhīm at the end of it.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]